A Guide to the Booth Tarkington Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Booth Tarkington Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7416-t
The collection consists of 90 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from David J. Holmes, 2002 August 1.
Scope and Content
Collection of letters, manuscripts and ephemera by, or relating to, Booth Tarkington, a portion from the papers of his secretary, Elizabeth (Betty) Trotter.
Original manuscripts in the collection include "Edgar XIV Title The Little Saw"; a silent film scenario in the "Edgar Pomeroy" series; a synopsis of the play "Colonel Satan" about Aaron Burr; a description in the hand of Trotter "About Wanton Molly"; a statement about American school children; an untitled article beginning "How shall 'we the prople' make up our minds which way to vote in November [1940?]; "Flanner House"; an untitled page beginning "A chain is no stronger than its weakest link"; a typescript "Blind eyes or wits" for a "Save your vision week"; a speech "The colonel and 1942"; an untitled tribute for "Big Murray"; manuscript beginning "Mr. Tarkington's nurses say they go in fear" by Elizabeth Trotter; an essay "Brain sand"'; and two original manuscripts in the hand of Eliabeth Trotter, possibly from Tarkington's dictation, beginning "Did you have a good time dear" and "Cynthia Weldon is my first cousin."
Topics in Tarkington's correspondence, several of which are in the hand of Trotter, include stories for publication; Robert H. Davis; vision problems and home remedies for blindness; possible collaboration with N. C. Wyeth; censorship of sexual references and "Anthony Adverse"; John Coffee's bill to transform the Federal Arts Project into a permanent government agency, Harry Byrd's opinion on the former, and income tax deductions for art purchases; economic and labor problems,the depression and the Works Progress Administration; the Munich Agreement; Picasso as the Father Divine of art; presidential term limits; his characters "Ames Lanning" and "Josephine" and creating characters readers like; World War II including an anecdote about plane spotting, a reference to a young acquaintance missing in action, and unfavorable comments on Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt; the rescue of stray dogs; and a severe winter storm at Kennebunkport.
Correspondents include Edward R. Burke, Frederick A. Duneka, Lloyd Frankenburg, Fanny Hurst, Ray Baker Harris, Robert Underwood Johnson, Fred Kelly, William Charles Lengel, Walter Moses, Adelaide W. Neall, Wellington Roe, Roger Livingston Scaife, [Abraham or Elkan?] Silberman, [Henry?] Pratt [Smith?], Mrs. William H. Trotter, Warrack Wallace, and a secretary to William H. Wilmer.
Correspondence of Mrs. William H. Trotter with her daughter Elizabeth, Allan A. Hunter, Henry G. Leach, and Robert Emmet MacAlarney chiefly concerns Tarkington. Topics include Scott Nearing and a coming class struggle, Lyell Rader, The Forum magazine, stage play "The poor nut," Tarkington's "Mirthful haven" and "Seventeen," Elizabeth's writing, the New Deal, John Main Coffee, and the European war.
Miscellaneous items include a comically illustrated bill; a contract with Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer; various printed reviews, advetisements, and two bulletins from the Indiana Committee for National Defense, 1941, and unidentified photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series: Series I. Manuscripts. -- Series II Subseries A. Correspondence of Booth Tarkington. -- Series II Subseries B. Correspondence about Booth Tarkington. -- Series III. Photographs, Printed and Miscellany
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - 1919 Original Manuscript "Edgar XIV Title The Little Saw," an unsigned holograph manuscript of a silent film scenario by Tarkington, in pencil on yellow paper with numerous revisions, deletions, and additions in the author's hand. Probably a draft for a silent movie in the "Edgar Pomeroy" series, produced by Goldwyn Pictures Corporation in 1919-1920. The text consists of the captions to appear in the film, headed "Printed" such as "What Mr. Pomeroy wanted for Christmas – but didn't expect" and descriptions of the actual scenes entitled "Picture" such as "Mr. Pomeroy in his law office – not an elaborate or very important one." AMs, 23 pages on 23 leaves (Box-folder 1:1)
  - [ca. 1930?] Synopsis of the play "Colonel Satan" written by Booth Tarkington about Aaron Burr, AMs, in pencil, on 1 l., 2 pages (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1932 September Manuscript "Note on Wanton Mally" for Doubleday, AMs, in pencil on orange paper, (oversize), 1 page
  - [1932?]"About Wanton Mally" Original manuscript in pencil on orange folio paper, unsigned, with revisions throughout, written in the hand of Elizabeth Trotter, possibly by dictation from Tarkington, with the text beginning, "Upon the surface Wanton Mally might appear to be a romantic fantasia decorated with Gallic grace-notes and somewhat irresponsibly executed in a seventeenth century key; on the contrary, it is the effort to decipher the meaning of a portrait ["The Ugly Lady"]. AMs, in pencil on orange paper, (oversize), 2 pages on 2 leaves
  - 1938 April 10 Statement about American Schoolchildren by Booth Tarkington, TMs, carbon copy, 1 page (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 1938 April 13 Quotation from Variety concerning the Reorganization Bill in Congress, TMs, 1 page (Box-folder 1:4)
  - [1940?] Untitled Article beginning, "How shall 'We the People' make up our minds which way to vote in November? All up and down the land there is a great clamor of voices shouting answers." The election in question was the 1940 presidential race between Franklin D. Roosevelt and Wendell Wilkie., TMsS, carbon copy; 6 pages on 6 leaves (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1941 Typescript "Flanner House" by Booth Tarkington, TMs, one a title page, carbon copy; 3 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:6)
  - [post 1941] Untitled Manuscript beginning "A chain is no stronger than its weakest link," possibly by Booth Tarkington, TMs, incomplete, 1 page (Box-folder 1:7)
  - 1942 March 8-14 Typescript "Blind Eyes or Wits" For "Save Your Vision Week," appeared in The Indiana Optometrist and The Indianapolis News, TMs, carbon copy, 1 page (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1942 October Speech "The Colonel and 1942" given by Booth Tarkington at the presentation of the Roosevelt Medal in New York, with envelope addressed to Mrs. William Henry Trotter, TMs, carbon copy, 5 pages on 5 leaves (Box-folder 1:9)
  - [1942 October?] Untitled Memorial Tribute for "Big Murray" [Harold Griffith Murray], a classmate of Tarkington's at Princeton University in 1893, published in The Princeton Alumni Weekly, TMs, carbon copy, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:10)
  - n.y. June 8"Notes on a Trip Up Williams Mountain, Albemarle Island," by an unknown author, TMs, 4 pages on 4 leaves (Box-folder 1:11)
  - n.d. Original Untitled Manuscript, with revision, by Elizabeth Trotter, with the text beginning, "Mr. Tarkington's nurses say that they go in fear - fear lest other nurses, rendered savage by envy, will have their lives. For Mr. Tarkington's popularity as a patient, like his popularity in other lives, is extreme. As Mr. Tarkington's amanuensis, and part-time hospital reader-aloud of detective stories, I am in a most justly exalted position, and I cannot avoid suspecting that I was asked to write this article in order that the entire nursing staff of Johns Hopkins hospital might feel avenged.", AMs, 5 pages on 5 leaves (Box-folder 1:12)
  - n.d. Christmas Greeting with a portion of "Beasley's Christmas Party" by Booth Tarkington, TMs, 1 page (Box-folder 1:13)
  - n.d. Essay "Brain Sand" about the dangers of losing our ability to remember, with penciled suggestions for additions and corrections throughout, possibly supplied by Booth Tarkington, with a full page of comments in pencil on the back of page five and addressed to "Elizabeth Trotter.", TMs, 5 pages on 5 leaves (Box-folder 1:14)
  - n.d. Original incomplete manuscript in pencil on orange folio paper of an untitled story, divided into two chapters and unsigned, with revisions throughout, written in the hand of Elizabeth Trotter, possibly by dictation from Tarkington, with the text beginning, "Did you have a good time, dear? Mrs. Carpenter incautiously asked her daughter, as the latter, dragging the heels of her cerise mules, came slowly into the dining-room to a late Sunday breakfast.", AMs, (oversize), 13 pages on 13 leaves
  - n.d. Original incomplete manuscript in pencil on orange folio paper of an untitled story, unsigned, with revisions throughout, written in the hand of Elizabeth Trotter, possibly by dictation from Tarkington, with the text beginning, "Cynthia Weldon is my first cousin, and I felt a trifle ashamed of myself when I read in a newspaper that she was to be one of the season's debutantes. 'Dear me!' I thought. 'Little Cynthia's coming-out!'", AMs,(oversize), 5 pages on 5 leaves
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Letters to and from Booth Tarkington
    - 1900 July 24 Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, apologizes for his delay in answering his note due to his difficulty with his eyes and unfamiliarity with dictation; writes he has nothing near completion that has not already been promised to someone for publication but he has begun a story that may be ready by late fall that could possibly suit him; and recalls a very pleasant evening at his house in '96., ALS, 2 pages on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - [1906 November 5] Booth Tarkington, Champigny-sur-Marne, France, to [Frederick A.] Duneka, writes "On receipt of your letter stating that you thought it better not to use "His Own People" in the mag. but would print it in the Weekly I cabled you (Harpers) to return the mss to me. This was because I felt that to place the story in the Weekly would do neither you & the Weekly nor the story and me any good; might work a contrary effect in fact." Tarkington goes on to explain his reasoning about the story. He also asks if he is going to reprint James De Mille's Castle in Spain as he did the others., ALS, 3 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:16)
    - 1928 November 12 Booth Tarkington to Elizabeth Trotter, thanks her for the article from Scribner's, whose author is an English professor who appears interested in students in English and who feels that everyone should read poetry. Tarkington believes that he knows the reason for this odd thought, "The sight of your house at Chestnut Hill, or of the one at Kennebunkport would convince anyone of that. They are secluded without being withdrawn; thoughtful, but not scholastic; and they seem to say, 'There is time here for everything worthwhile.", ALS, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:17)
    - 1930 April 25 Telegram from Fannie Hurst, New York City, to Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, concerning the severe accident which placed Robert H. Davis in the hospital for months, asking Tarkington to submit one thousand words to appear in a column in The New York Sun called "Bob Davis Recalls" to help him out, 1 page (Box-folder 1:18)
    - [1930] Unsigned draft of a letter to [William Charles ?] Lengel, in pencil on orange paper with revisions, written in the hand of Elizabeth Trotter, probably from dictation by Booth Tarkington, saying "Herewith I am sending you the third of the stories, which was well toward completion before I went to S.H. Recalling that "Penrod" had appeared in the Post & Everybody before it moved to the Cosmopolitan, years ago, I hadn't realized that the latter might prefer, with the changing times, not to have "Mr. M" move in with his special baggage, ie. this third story is a 'Massey' one, having got so far along before your hint of preference was received." He assures him that the next three do not have Massey as a character and the fourth "Cider of Normandy" has an "American in Paris background.", AL, 1 page (Box-folder 1:19)
    - [1930] Unsigned draft of a letter to [William Charles ?] Lengel, in pencil on orange paper with revisions, written in the hand of Elizabeth Trotter, probably from dictation by Booth Tarkington, encloses the fourth story "Cider of Normandy" with its Parisian flavor, and notes that the "next story will revert to New England but not to Mr. Massey." He also plans for one of the six stories to be serious and not humorous in intent, with its meaning conveyed by "calamity in the drama.", AL, 1 page (Box-folder 1:19)
    - 1931 February 16 Elizabeth Kerr, Secretary to Dr. William H. Wilmer, to Booth Tarkington, returning two typed letters (enclosed) which were sent to Tarkington while he was a patient at Johns Hopkins Hospital, discussing home remedy treatments for blindness. Kerr writes that Dr. Wilmer really enjoyed seeing the letters and she promises to help him secure a photograph of Wilmer on his next visit. The two letters enclosed were from American Indian of the Piscataway Treaty Nation, Al Proctor S. Marsh (1872-?), New York City, January 31, 1931, and an unidentified correspondent from Modesto, California, January 31, 1931. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - 1935 May 17 Booth Tarkington, Kennebunkport, Maine, to [Roger Livingston] Scaife, regrets that he did not have time to call him during his brief pause in Boston but would very much like to meet Scaife and Mr. Sedgwick for lunch in Kennebunkport, Maine, if it could be arranged between now and December., TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:21)
    - 1935 September 4 Booth Tarkington, Kennebunkport, Maine, to [Roger Livingston] Scaife, informs him that there is almost no chance of being able to do a book with Mr. Wyeth within the next two years. Tarkington then suggests they try "one of the new Maine writers," Isabel Hopestill Carter, who wrote the book Shipmates and has "the Maine feeling and a fine literary honesty in the expression of it.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:22)
    - 1936 September 1 Booth Tarkington, Kennebunkport, Maine, to Ray Baker Harris, discusses censorship and the circumstances of the publication of his short story "His Own People" in the Saturday Evening Post which had been refused by Harper's due to the moral objection "that the young man kissed a lady on her shoulder. That 'wasn't done' in 1906. Nowadays we have "Anthony Adverse" and complete copulative description - recommended by educational authorities for high school reading!" Tarkington goes on to mention his article in the [Saturday Evening] Post "When Is It Dirt?" explaining "my own generation had really won the struggle for freedom of expression in print but that after the battle the camp followers arrived, committing excesses upon the field. The camp followers are having things their own way now, certainly, collecting dirt to sell, and of course they're not "daring" - camp followers never are.", TLS, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:23)
    - 1937 September 29 Booth Tarkington to Mr. Silberman, a New York City art dealer, complains that he has not seen a whale all summer long, regrets that he left before meeting his English visitors, who soon sail for home. He describes the activities of one of them, "Mr. Warner, 78, dances wildly every evening with Betty - tangos, Russian jigs, minuets and maudlin-like interpretative dancing." Tarkington also encloses the October issue of the little magazine of the Literary Guild, with advance notices of his book Rumblin Galleries for which Silberman supplied some background knowledge, as well as sending a copy to Mr. Vose in Boston since "they're calling him 'Mr. Rumblin' in Boston and elsewhere, and your brother circulated the rumor that I was Vose Galleries 'ideal client.' He also mentions having to decline an invitation to give an art lecture at the Minneapolis Museum of Art due to his health where "like your brother's favorite art lecturer, I could have mentioned my yacht.", ALS, 2 pages on 1 leaf, in pencil on orange paper (Box-folder 1:24)
    - 1938 April 28 Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, to Lloyd Frankenberg, an enclosure with a note from Bet to Mussy, dated Thursday, where she describes the enclosed letter as a "monumental letter Mr. T's just written to the indignant young Poet of Greenwich Village, N.Y. who wrote in a restrained rage after he'd read the reprint of Mr. T's letter to Mr. Coffee in the Herald Tribune." Tarkington was responding to Frankenberg's criticism of his letter to Mr. Coffee which he had not known would be printed. The point of disagreement appears to be the success and necessity of government subsidies of artists, good or bad, during the Depression and the bill sponsored by Representative John Coffee (D-WA) to transform the Federal Arts Project into a permanent government agency, the Bureau of Fine Arts., TL, carbon copy 10 pages on 10 leaves (Box-folder 1:25)
    - 1938 April 29 Booth Tarkington to Wellington Roe, Writers' Committee for a Federal Bureau of Fine Arts, New York, disagrees that he has fifty contemporaries but if he does at his age he does not wish to enter into controversy with them and feels physically unable to come personally to the Conference to defend his position on the proposed Federal Arts Bill. He also explains how his letter to Mr. Coffee came to be published and suggests that Roe read Senator Byrd's article from the April Atlantic Monthly to the Conference instead of his letter to Coffee. He also suggests a better approach to help painters and sculptors would be to permit the purchase of works of art to be deducted from income taxes., TL, carbon copy, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:26)
    - 1938 August 5 Booth Tarkington, Kennebunkport, Maine, to Mr. Norcutt, thanks him for his birthday wishes and addresses his question about why human beings work at trying to make things, "I've tried to give hints as to what the answer may be in a novel of mine called Presenting Lily Mars; but of course it is a question that must be answered by everyone in a different way.", TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:27)
    - 1938 October 6 Booth Tarkington to "Dear Warrack," [Warrack Wallace?] reviews the history of events in Europe from 1918 leading up to the rise of Hitler in Germany and the current status of the Treaty of Versailles. They were apparently discussing the repercussions of the Munich Agreement signed by Adolf Hitler, Neville Chamberlain, Edouard Daladier, and Benito Mussolini, on September 29, 1938, which transferred the Sudetenland to Germany and the subsequent march of the German army into the Sudetenland on October 1, 1938., TL, carbon copy, 4 pages on 4 leaves (Box-folder 1:28)
    - 1939 January 30 Booth Tarkington, Indianapolis, Indiana, to [Abraham?] Silberman, encloses on thousand dollars payment on the Titian painting, leaving a debt of two thousand, and expresses his pleasure at seeing Mr. and Mrs. Elkan Silberman while they were in town, and hopes to see him and Dr. Ganz soon., TLS, 1 page (Box-folder 1:29)
    - 1939 May 7"C. Coolidge, Jr." [Booth Tarkington] to "From a letter to Fred Kelly," discusses the economic woes of the times, the limitations of money, the causes of unemployment, the Works Progress Administration and its use of its relief recipients to vote in elections, and dangers of the society family administration who did not understand business, TL, carbon copy, 6 pages, on 6 leaves (Box-folder 1:30)
    - 1939 May 29[Booth Tarkington] to "Letter to Fred Kelly continued," describes the political characteristics of the Nazis, communism, and a Republic, concluding, "I say: no liberty except under a Republic governed by as little Law as enables men to compete for their own profit without openly robbing one another!", TL, carbon copy, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:31)
    - 1939 May 29[Booth Tarkington] to "Dear Mr. Secretary," discusses current economic and labor problems, which he summarizes as three "egoisms" fighting for power, employers, labor leaders, and politicians, "3 egoisms working to get Power out of all us other fellers, the workingman, Which we going to be Fer? The one that - promises us the most, of course-if we believe him. Which one had we better be Fer. The one that'll give us the most. We'd better look into those promises!", TL, carbon copy, 4 pages on 4 leaves (Box-folder 1:32)
    - 1939 December 26 Booth Tarkington, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Mr. Silberman, promises to look into a rumor about the supposed acquisition of a Titian in Indianapolis; will leave in a week to allow Betty to recover her strength; Mrs. Tarkington was called suddenly to New York by the violent illness of Miss Keifer with food poisoning; and writes "I hope you aren't buying any Picassos; I think there are signs that the whole circus is beginning to droop - just beginning but the flop will follow. Father Devine, too, begins to look punctured after a long success, and, since Pic is the Father Divine of Art, it's appropriate that they're on their way out together.", ALS, 2 pages on 1l. (Box-folder 1:33)
    - 1940 August 29[Booth Tarkington] to the Honorable Senator Edward R. Burke, Committee on the Judiciary, writes concerning the reasons he supports limiting the tenure of the office of the Presidency, TL, carbon copy, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:34)
    - 1941 March 5[Booth Tarkington] to "Most Honored Guest of Sigma Chi," [Fred], expresses his high regard for Fred, his fellow Brother of the Delta Delta chapter of Sigma Chi, by letter since he cannot be present to speak in person, TL, carbon copy, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:35)
    - 1941 December 30[Booth Tarkington] to A. Neall, Saturday Evening Post, writes concerning his character "Ames Lanning" and about serials in general, "I should keep a reminder-slogan before me on the wall of my workroom: 'Reader's got to LIKE somebody!' -I'm too much interested in the yoomanbeins as such, in my stories, making 'em out of realities that swarm them together from mosaic memory cubes - too absorbed in that to remember that the reader, too, isn't (in numbers) of this persuasion. He has to like the important people, as in some measure, replicas of himself, or else they must seem to be his neighbor (exposed) or they must be so queer, and probably monstrous, as to interest him in the fairy story of their doings, or else one of them must be the reader himself (a perfect being who is also the author) having wunfle [wonderful?] adventures and love affairs vicariously.", TL, typescript copy, 1 page (Box-folder 1:36)
    - 1942 January 19 Booth Tarkington to "Dear Pratt" [Henry Pratt Smith?] concerning the state of the war, tells a humorous story of a local enemy plane spotter from Kennebunkport who saw a black plane overhead and "hurried back to the village and reported the black plane to Mitchell Field - in a letter." He goes on to compare the current time to World War I, 1918, after Ludendorff had thrust through to Amiens, when all the military authorities, diplomats, and newspapers were gloomy. Even after the Germans fell behind the Hindenburg Line, they all predicted a long war ahead. (oversize), ALS, in pencil, on orange folio paper, 2 pages